[Music]
hello welcome to episode six of the
inventory tutorial series in this
episode we are going to be covering the
dynamic display so in the minute we've
got our static display so there's always
10 slots and these slots fill up with
our tomatoes and our potatoes or um so
these fill up you know and these are
static these are always the same
um but we have a small chest here and a
big chest and we want to be able to
access the small chest and the big chest
and we're going to have a window that
pops up and displays their own um
individual
inventories but you know we don't want
to have to make a different screen based
on
every sort of inventory size that we
want because we may want something to
only have one inventory slot something
to our 30. we want a bit bit more of a
flexible system we could do that by
making a script that derives from our
inventory display class so just like our
static inventory display inherits from
inventory display we're going to make a
dynamic in the tree display script so
let's just right click create c-sharp
script
and we'll call this the dynamic
inventory
display and let's just have a look at
how this is going to work so this is the
test project here so if we hit play yes
i've got my hotbar here i can press tab
i can press b on the keyboard and my
backpack inventory comes up
and i can go over here and i can access
the small chest which you know here has
i think that's 10 10 slots or we can go
across to our big chest then this has
got 20 slots
and our backpack has
50 slots i believe yeah so there we go
we've got 50 slots in our backpack so
you can see how that's scaled up um i
need to play with the anchoring because
it's gone up to the top of the screen
but we can we can do that we can sort
that so let's go back to
the project that we're currently
actually working through let's just open
up our dynamic inventory script so again
our dynamic inventory display is going
to
inherit from
inventory display which is the kind of
base class so let's replace mono
behavior with inventory display
and let's just get rid of these
let's get rid of the update function
and get rid of this comment and we can
just say
protected override
void start
and we want to say
base
dot start but before we do the base
start well what we can do
is we can subscribe to our inventory
holders on dynamic inventory display
requested event so we say inventory
holder
dot on dynamic inventory display
requested
and i'm gonna
subscribe
method that we've not created yet called
refresh
dynamic inventory
display
uh no just let's call it refresh dynamic
inventory and we can even make this just
public
void
refresh
dynamic
inventory
and this next needs to take in an
inventory system
and i'm just going to call this the in
to display
and here we can see our inventory system
is equal to the in to display
so inventory system is the
[Music]
inventory system here this is the
inventory system
um on our inventory display
and we're just setting that to the
inventory to display that we're bringing
in
we're bringing that in from our
inventory holder script on our inventory
holder script we've got this unity
action which is static so we can access
it from anywhere like we've just done
and it's called on inventory on dynamic
industry display requested
and it passes in an inventory system and
we're not currently invoking this
anywhere yet uh we will do
in a second we'll work on the getting
the player's backpack working first
and then if we have time in this video
we'll work on the chests if not we'll do
the chests in the next video let's just
see how far along we get so let's go
back over to our dynamic inventory
display class and let's just finish
implementing this so
we have a red squiggle that's because we
aren't implementing the abstract
class
the abstract method that we made in our
abstract inventory display class and
that's our assigned slots function
so let's just get rid of our
system not implemented error but the
first thing that we want to do
on assign slots for our dynamic
inventory displays we want to clear all
of the slots that were there from the
last time that we looked at an inventory
so
you can see that when we were accessing
the chests in the project my test
project that i've already got set up
i
you know the actual slots delete when we
close the um
we'll close the panel and then when we
go to open up the panel of a different
chest
it'll clear all the slots it'll just
delete all of the prefabs and then it'll
spawn them back in
it'll spawn the correct amount back in
so instead of 20 slots
they'll be 10 or 5 or however many the
inventory display has or needs to like
actually request so the first thing
we'll do here is we'll do private void
and let's make a method called clear
slots
and we need to be using um
system.link here so what we're going to
do here is we're going to say for each
variable
item in transform
dot cast
transform
this is going to get all of the um
children on our transform so this is
going to sit on the top level object and
it's going to have ui slots underneath
it so it's going to get all of those
and we just need to say destroy
item dot game object
now a more efficient way of doing this
would be to use object pooling
so instead of destroying and
instantiating new slots we could just
disable them and clear them and uh
add them back to a pool this isn't an
object pooling tutorial so we're not
gonna um
do that here we're just gonna act
directly destroy them but just know that
that is an option and if you want to go
and look into object pooling you can you
can do so and this is that would be a
better way to do this but for now for
what we need this this works fine so as
well as this
and destroying the actual objects we
want to clear out the um slot dictionary
so we can say if slot dictionary is not
equal to null
then slot dictionary dot clear
and again just to remind ourselves the
slot dictionary
is the dictionary that pairs a ui slot
with an inventory system slot
so we clear that out when we clear the
slots so in our assign slot function we
can just say clear slots
and then we're going to do a similar
thing to what we do here in our static
inventory display when we assign our
slots we're going to pair
we're going to pair a slot with our
inventory systems
inventory slots um
array so first thing we're going to do
is because we've cleared the slots and
we've cleared this
we can all we can just make a new
dictionary over the top to make sure
that it is definitely clear
so new dictionary inventory slot ui
inventory slot is the key and value
and we can say that if
in
to display
equals null
then let's just return out of this
because we don't want to start um
accessing it if it's null so it's just a
good way of checking to make sure that
we're not going to get any um null uh
reference exceptions
and then we can say 4
int equals i
whilst i is less than the inv to display
dot inventory size
we're going to make a new
um reference to a ui slot which we are
going to instantiate so instantiate
and i'm just going to say slot prefab
which is a variable we'll set up in just
a second and then i'm going to put the
parent as this transform
and let's come up to the top and let's
just make a serialized field
protected
inventory slot ui
slot pre slot pre
fab
i'm just making this protected just in
case down the line we want to um
inherit from this class for example we
may want
um dynamic inventory displays to
we may want some of the functionality
that this provides but expand on it a
bit more for example um
npcs with a shop
they would have multiple probably
dynamic inventory displays or they'd
have some custom functionality that
chests for example wouldn't need
and so we're just making that protected
just in case down the line we want to
access it we don't need to come back
here something i've um i forgot to do
because we're subscribing to this event
here we just want to unsubscribe from it
if we um need to so i'm just going to
say on destroy i'm just going to say
minus equals refresh dynamic inventory
that's something that
we need to do
um but let's come back to our assign
slot so we're going to get a variable
called ui slot and it's going to
instantiate this slot prefab and then
just store a reference to
the
the specific slot prefab that has been
created and then we're gonna add it to
our slot dictionary
and this ui slot is gonna be the key
and the um
value is going to be the inventory to
display
dot inventory slots
i
because you know we're in this loop
and it'll go for this is going to create
the exact amount of slots that it needs
and it'll pair the slot with the current
uh index the wheel that we're on in the
for loop
and then we can say ui slot
dot init
for initialize we can pass in the
inventory to display uh inventory slots
i
and then we can just call ui slot
um
update ui slot here
so this is just like our static
inventory display
so we're doing a loop we are adding the
slots but we just because the slots
haven't been defined here
and up under our
base dot star i'm just going to assign
slot
inventory system
and pass in our inventory system i'm
just going to do that once so it clears
it out and it sets up anything that it
needs to set up found that not doing
that here
when we
access it the first time
[Music]
in game it wouldn't actually show
anything that was already in the
inventory so we just need to um
run this method uh just once here
and that sorts that out so if we
press control s to save that now let's
just go back over into
unity and let's go to our canvas
and underneath our canvas let's just
open this up so here i'm just going to
make an empty object i'm going to create
empty and i'm going to call this the
inventory
ui
controller
i'm just going to make our hotbar and
our mouse object apparent of the
inventory ui and then for our inventory
um and then underneath our inventory ui
controller i'm gonna right click create
ui and i'm gonna choose
panel
i'm just gonna call this um
dynamic
inventory
and i'll bring this just up
above the mouse object
just so the mouse object renders on top
of the ui element that we're going to
make and i'm just going to add
add component and we're going to add our
dynamic inventory display
and i'm just going to drag in our mouse
object uh item to our dynamic inventory
display
and i'm going to go over to our prefabs
and i'm going to drag in our slot prefab
over to it so now let's get um a content
size fitter added to this
and we can set this to preferred size
and then we want a grid
layout group
we've got our grid layout group
and under padding i'm just going to put
some padding in so 10 10
for cell size i'll have that at 100 and
i'll just put some spacing in as well
for child alignment i'm going to choose
um upper center
and constraint i'm going to have a fixed
column count i'm just going to have 10
columns as our fixed column count
so if we just drag our prefab directly
under our dynamic inventory we can see
kind of what that's going to look like
so
let's just add them in
so you can see that how that's going to
look when we add sort of more and more
so that's with 51 slots
which is probably too many anyway so
let's just delete all of those out
press ctrl s to save
so we've got our dynamic inventory here
let's go up to our inventory ui
controller and let's try and get this
set up and work in so we need to make a
script on our inventory controller so
let's go back to our ui scripts folder
and let's right click create c sharp
script and we'll call this the inventory
ui
controller
let's open this up in visual studio so
here for the inventory ui controller
i'm going to keep the update method
and i'm just going to get a public
uh dynamic inventory display
and i'll call this the inventory panel
which is what we've just made
and here i'm going to um oh
make a on enable function and on enable
i'm going to say inventory holder dot
on
dynamic inventory display requested
and i will put a display
inventory
method which we're going to create
and then on disable
we'll just want to unsubscribe that
method from it as well just to be
safe so we can minus equals display
inventory
and then in our display
function which we'll make here void
display
inventory
which will take in the
inventory system
in to display
so this is going to say inventory panel
dot game object dot set active to true
and inventory panel dot refresh dynamic
inventory and pass in the in to display
which actually thinking about it that
makes this redundant um
we don't need to do this so let's just
uh
comment that out
and we can actually get rid of this as
well we don't want we don't actually
need to um
call it on start
so let's get rid of those
the reason that we don't need to call it
on start is because in our inventory ui
controller when we set it to active
we're refreshing it anyway
passing in the inventory display so now
we're only subscribing to this event in
one kind of place which is fine that's
that's not which is a bit cleaner than
subscribing here and calling it twice
and we can actually say here in our
refresh dynamic inventory we can call
clear slots here
take it out of a sign slot
and we can call a sign slot here
so a little bit of refactoring so now on
our ui on our inventory ui controller
this is going to receive this request to
display inventory it's going to set the
panel to active and then it's going to
refresh the dynamic inventory which is
going to clear out any old slots it's
going to update the inventory to display
and then it's going to assign um slots
which will do do all this
so let's save that go back over to our
inventory ui controller so let's just
test this is all working now so let's
say using unity engine dot input system
in our update function on the ui
controller we can say if
key
keyboard
dot current dot i'm gonna say
b key
for like bags so if the b key dot is
dot was pressed this frame
then we're going to
um
we're going to bypass this method and
we're just going to display inventory
and we'll make a new inventory system
with a size of let's say 30. so we'll
just uh
you know we're just making a new
inventory system here when we press the
b key and we're displaying that and
actually let's just see this working so
we can actually say random.range
and we'll say between
20 and
30.
so if the b key was pressed display the
inventory and create an inventory system
to display with a random size of between
20 and 30. then we can say if
the inventory panel dot gameobject dot
is
active in hierarchy
so if it's set as active
and
keyboard
dot current
dot escape key
dot was pressed this frame then let's
set the panel back to false let's close
our bags so let's just check this is
working
we can go over to um hit play and we
need to add the
inventory ui script to our controller we
need to just
assign our dynamic inventory display
and what we can do is we can
set it to false
in the awake method so we just we know
that it's going to be um
closed already when we first start
so let's just set it to false if it's
not already so you can see that the
dynamic imagery is enabled at the minute
when we hit play it'll um disappear
so we've got our inventory here
we can press b to open our bags and you
can see that it's created our inventory
slots if i press escape it'll close the
panel
and they are still there um but when i
press b again it'll delete them and
it'll make another one of a different
size and we can press escape
b so you can see that here we're now
getting a panel
that responds dynamically to different
inventory sizes
now obviously if i put a
something in this when i press escape
it's getting deleted the inventory
system we're making so those items will
just um you know disappear so let's work
on doing this so it's actually permanent
so let's make a chest now
so let's go back over to our inventory
system
uh project
and we'll get rid of this we don't need
um
that let's keep this one though so we
can press the escape panel to close any
sort of chests that we're looking at and
bring that down so we can actually see
that so it's a bit more uh neat
so we've got um
so yeah let's make our
chest script now so here let's go over
to
our project again let's go into our
inventory scripts
and let's make a new c-sharp script
called chest
inventory let's open that up and this is
going to um
inherit from inventory holder
and we're going to get rid of the start
and update function
and we're actually going to use um
using unity engine dot events
because we're gonna
need to implement um a unity action
which will pass in the type of i
interactable which is an interface we're
going to make in just a second
and this is going to be called on
interaction
complete
which we can put get and set
we won't actually use this in this
tutorial but it's going to be enforced
by this i interactable which we're going
to make now so let's go back over to our
project and i'm going to make um
a new folder in our scripts folder
called interfaces
and we need to make an
interface for all of our interactable
items in the game so c sharp script and
let's call this i
interactable
so let's open up that script
and this again is going to be using
unity
engine.events it's going to be an
interface so let's get rid of mono
behavior and public
interface i interactable
so it's going to need a public unity
action
which passes in a type of interactable
called on
interaction
complete with a
get and set
we're going to have a method called
public
void
interact
which will take in um an interactor
which is another script we're going to
have to make i'm just going to call that
interactor
and it'll pass out a bool
of whether the interaction was um
successful
and we also want a public
void
and
interaction
so let's just uh copy this
let's go over to um
unity and in our scripts folder let's
right-click create c-sharp script and
let's call it interactor
so now that's um
that's fine that's filled in let's just
line that back up i'll work on the
interactor script in just a second
let's go back over to our chest
inventory
and make sure this is inheriting
that interface so i interactable
and we should get a squiggle in a second
yep so we press alt and enter
it'll add those um the interface's
methods let's get rid of them and i'm
actually going to move interact up above
the end interaction just
because it's a bit neater like that way
so interact is going to be a method that
was that's called when we try and
interact with the chest so when we open
the chest so obviously here we need to
um
say on dynamic imagery display dot
requested is anyone listening out for
this event and if it is let's invoke it
and pass in our inventory system
so again this is deriving from inventory
holder this event is on our inventory
holder and so is our inventory system so
we're gonna call that event when we are
interacted with and we're gonna um
pass out
we're gonna invoke that and pass in our
inventory system and then we can say
interact successful is equal to true
so we're not actually going to use an
interaction here
this is just enforced by an eye
interactable
interface
stand line maybe you want a event um on
interaction complete to fire when
something happens then you'll call that
in the in end interaction function
and for example
so for example if your player moves away
from the chest that you could call on
interaction complete and be listening
out for that on the ui controller
and then so instead of pressing escape
then so instead of pressing escape
you'd be listening out for that event
and that would set the panel to false
instead
but i'm just going to keep it like
i'm just going to try and keep it simple
so we're just going to
interact with the chest and we'll call
the on dynamic inventory display
requested and we'll just pass in our
inventory system so now we need to be
able to actually interact with the chest
and that's what this interactor
component is going to be this is going
to sit on our player so let's go build
that quickly but there's lots of
different ways to do this and the way
i'm going to do it is i'm going to make
a public transform
and call this interaction point
i'm going to have a public layer mask
called interaction
layer
i'll have a public float with it which
is the interaction
um
point
radius and i'll set this equal to one f
and i want a public
bull called is interacting
with a get and private set
and in our private void update function
we're going to make a variable called
colliders and we're going to equal this
to physics
dot overlap sphere
and we're going to pass in the interact
point
dot position
as well as the
interaction point radius is our radius
so as we're walking around if we
interact with anything um
you know on the
and then we need to pass in our
interaction layer as well as the third
parameter
so as we're walking around if we overlap
anything that um
is on that interaction layer
at that position and within this sphere
that we're making
it'll store
it in a collider array which you can see
there so collider array physics.overlap
sphere that's what it returns so this
will be a collider array called
colliders
and now we can say the if
and we'll say keyboard
dot
we need to be using sorry using unity
engine dot input system
so here we could say if keyboard dot
current dot and then whatever key you
want i'm gonna use the
e key
dot
was pressed this frame
then we're gonna loop over
all of the colliders that we are
currently um
overlapping so colliders.length
i plus plus
i'm going to say var interactable
is equal to colliders i
dot get component
i interactable
so
we're going to check every collider that
we're interacting with to see whether
it's got the interactable interface on
it
if that's successful interactable won't
be null so we can say if interactable
is not equal to null
then we've successfully found an
interactable item which is what this
interface indicates
so we can just say
um start
interaction
and we can pass in the interactable
and all i'm going to do there is this is
going to be a
um void
start interaction
which takes in an i interactable
called interactable
i'm just going to say
interactable.interact and it's going to
pass
itself in
and get back out there interact
successful
uh bull
the reason i've spanned this out as its
own method because in your movement
script for example you may want to be
checking the interactor component to see
whether there is interacting bull is set
to true and if it is true you may want
to disable movement
so here you could say is interacting
is set to true
and then at some point you could have an
end interaction um
you know an end interaction
method that sets is interacting back to
fault and you'll call this somewhere in
your script depending on
your code so for example
we could say here
if we if collider's dot length is zero
then we're not interacting or if we
become if we move a certain distance
away from the thing that we collided
with we could choose this uh this is
just a way of keeping track of what your
the interactor is doing it's not going
to have any effect on
you know what we're doing but hopefully
this is just something extra that you
can expand upon
again this is a tutorial on an inventory
system not an interaction system or
something like that if you want me to
cover this more in detail let me know in
the comments below but just know that
all we need is
this
interactable.interact so we're
overlapping anything here
and the e key was pressed this frame
then we're going to search for the
through the overlaps going to try and
find the interactable component on all
of these colliders and if we find one
we'll start our interaction which we'll
call interact
on our interactable which in this case
would hopefully be our chest inventory
which will just say on dynamic inventory
display requested passing in its
inventory system
and then our dynamic inventory display
would show that
so let's get this all set up so we can
get that working and i think that would
make a good point to end the video so
we've got our player movement script on
our player let's just add our interactor
script
and we need an interaction point so
under our player let's make an empty
and that's zero zero let's just call
that interaction
point
let's move it forward and i'm actually
just gonna um
give it a little
gizmo so we can see it in the scene
and we can
assign the interaction point on our
player script
on our interaction layer we can make a
new layer
and we'll call it um interactable
and then we'll go back to our player and
we'll choose the interactable layer as
our interaction layer and our radius um
let's set it to let's just leave it at
one for now and let's go over to our
small chest
let's add a chest inventory component to
it
and we'll say the small chest can have
an inventory size of 10.
and
we'll make sure that it's got a box
collider on
on the actual um inventory on the chest
so let's bring this up
one
point five maybe there we go and let's
remove the
colliders from the cubes underneath it
so we'll just remove components
set our small chest onto the
interactable layer and we can change the
children as well it doesn't really
matter
for our big chest let's again add a box
collider let's bring it up 0.5
increase the scale on the uh x to just
match the shape
of our um
[Music]
chest
get our cubes remove the box collider
go back to big
chest set its layer to the interactable
layer yes change children
let's give this a chest inventory script
and let's say the chest inventory has a
size of 20
so our small one's got a size of 10.
so let's see if this works and if it
doesn't let's debug it so we'll hit play
pick up some items on the way
so you can see here that our little
yellow point
let's fly over here our yellow point is
over
is inside our chest
you can see that i've pressed the button
and the the panel has come up we can
press escape
to get rid of it we can press e so i
opened up the big chest so we press e
the big chest with 20 slots opens
press escape to close it and come over
here press e the small chest opens press
escape to close it
we can open it back up with e we can put
our tomatoes in it we can
press escape to close it
we can pick up some potatoes
open up our big
chest we can store our
potatoes
press escape go back over to our
tomatoes
press e to open it our tomatoes are
there
press shift split them we can do all of
the same stuff we can you know leave our
stacks there
like this
presses
press escape
walk over press e on our big chest
get a potato back out
maybe leave three in put a tomato in
press escape walk back over here
access this chest all of our tomatoes
are there and this is because obviously
over our chest imagery system
when we close the panel
all of our inventory slots stay there so
if we press escape obviously the chest
inventory script has its inventory
system on it and that's now full of
those items so they exist in memory even
when we're not actively viewing them
so that kind of works exactly as you
would expect it and we can move them
again get them here you'll see that
we've got one tomato in slot one
let's combine these so now we've got
four tomatoes these are all null now
because they're empty so we can pick
them up put them back in our inventory
hit escape
pick up some more stuff
everything is working as we would expect
so hopefully i explained the interaction
system okay i did very much gloss over
it and if you have any problems or would
like to see a another series on the
interaction sort of script and how we
can get that working in a bit more
detail do let me know in the comments
below but i think that will do us for
now i think that's a good place to leave
it we've got the chest set up and
working it all came together quite
quickly at the end as always if you're
watching this as the videos go up weekly
uh the full series is complete and
already up over on patreon which is
patreon.com forward slash dan posh and
you can find a link for that in the
description as well as the full series
you'll also find the project files so at
the end of each episode i'm exporting
the scripts kind of as is like this
project where we are now
i'm saving that out as a package so you
better compare your um so you'd be able
to compare your scripts with my scripts
to see if anything's going wrong
if you do want any help with anything if
you've got any questions either leave a
comment below or better yet join the
discord server because over on discord
it's a bit easier to get real-time
feedback and you can share your scripts
easily you can share code excerpts a
link for the discord is in the
description below as well in the next
episode we'll work on the players
backpack system so they've got the
hotbar and um if we press b it'll open
up a dynamic backpack display
and when we walk over the items if the
hot bar's full they'll go into the
player's backpack instead
so that'll be in episode 7 which is the
next episode which will air in a week if
you're watching these as they go out
but in the meantime thanks for watching
and i'll see you in the next one bye
you